Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
- Series IV: National Refugee Service, undated, 1939-1945; Boxes 4 and 5.
  - National Refugee Service - Relief Work, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Copy of invitation to Razovsky's lectures at three venues., undated, October 24, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Attached is the program mentioned in Item #2.
    - "How Does the Refugee Get Here?" by Razovsky., October 28, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Discusses U.S. quotas and general immigration regulations.
    - Report on immigration law in Mexico., October 30, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Lists each article of law, including a list of countries with and without quota limits.
    - Copy of letter from Robert Pilpel, Secretary, Subcommittee on Refugee Aid in Central and South America to Luisa Klabin Lorch, São Paulo, Brazil., November 30, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Lorch previously wrote that she is organizing a committee to aid Polish Jews. Pilpel answers her question regarding sending clothing to refugees in Poland and refers her to Razovsky regarding bringing Polish refugee children to Brazil.
    - Memo from Mr. Greenleigh to Dr. Haber., January 6, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Concerning Greenleigh's conference with Mr. Asofsky of HIAS on January 3rd. Designates which agency will handle specific immigration activities: HIAS, NCJW, or NRS.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Lorch., November 19 and December 7, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Very few immigrants can leave Poland, committees are now being organized to help Polish refugees; there is a possibility of getting children still in Vienna. Attached is a memo from Razovsky to Robert Pilpel enclosing Dr. Ludwig Lorch's letter dated November 19th. Following is Dr. Ludwig Lorch's letter to the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, translated from German, dated November 19, 1939. Dr. Lorch reports on the situation for European Jewish refugees in Brazil.
    - Memo from Razovsky to Miss Marcuse., December 7, 1939 and January 8, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Razovsky quotes a report received from Luisa Klabin Lorch, São Paulo, Brazil regarding admitting children to Brazil from war zones. Attached is a letter from Razovsky to Lorch, (See Item #9).
    - Executive Office, Memo #40, from Dr. William Haber., January 15, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      All new applications for transportation assistance for migration to the U.S. and other countries (except for England) must now be referred to HIAS. NRS will handle the requests from England.
    - "On The European Refugees in Shanghai," by the Friends' Centre in Shanghai., April 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Reply to questions asked by the American Friends' service Committee. Contains background of refugee situation in Shanghai, describes committees who perform refugee relief, condition of refugee camp, future of refugees in China.
    - "Re: Navicerta," by Razovsky., April 3, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Concerns refugees now in the U.S. whose baggage is still being held by neutral European ports.
    - "Cases Successfully Handled by the National Refugee Service for Temporary Asylum in England.", April 15, 1940; 2 copies. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Memo from Lotte Marcuse, German-Jewish Children's Aid to Razovsky., May 8, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Kaete Rosenheim, Reichvereinigung der Juden in Deitschland, Berlin, Germany, had written Marcuse asking for possibilities of admitting refugee children into South American countries.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Louisa Lorch, São Paulo, Brazil., May 8, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Asks Lorch to send her organization's constitution and activities' description to Mrs. Louis Feigenblatt, President of the new Ladies Aid Society in San Jose, Costa Rica. Writes that Dr. Davidson has recently undergone an operation.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Jacques Zatvan (her cousin), Paris, France., May 9, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Razovsky has forwarded her cousin's affidavit to the American Consul in Paris.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Kaete Rosenheim, Reichvereinigung der Juden in Deitschland, Berlin, Germany., May 13, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Encloses a statement on possibilities for trainees in the Sosua estate in the Dominican Republic; also refers Rosenheim to Lorch in Brazil. Rosenheim is searching for admitting ports for children.
    - Summary of Frederick W. Borchard's Report on Refugee Situation in Buenos Aires, Argentina, May 26, 1940., May-June 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Attached are the following reports: Report on Chile, by Frederick W. Borchardt, June 13, 1940; Report on Bolivia, by Frederick W. Borchardt, June 12, 1940; Report on Uruguay, by Frederick W. Borchardt, May 16, 1940; Report concerning the loan fund administered by the Asociacion Filantropica Israelita of Montevideo, Uruguay, by Adolfo Hirsch, May 8, 1940.
    - Letter from Razovsky to the Lorchs in São Paulo, Brazil., June 29, 1940 and July 9, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Mr. Borchardt had just returned, Dr. Davidson is well again and has gone back to work. Attached is a letter from the Lorches to Razovsky and Davidson.
    - Translation of German letter from Reichsvereinigung., July 1 and 4, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Thanking Razovsky for her letter of May 13, 1940 (See Item #18). Enclosed is a copy of a letter written in German from Kaete Rosenheim to Louisa Lorch, São Paulo, July 1, 1940. The English translation follows.
    - Letter from Rosenheim to Razovsky in German, with following English translation., July 11, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      She asks about immigration permits for children in the Philippines.
    - Letter from Razovsky to Kaete Rosenheim, Berlin, Germany., July 22, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Responding to the July 4th letter (See Item #21). Razovsky does not know just what the present situation is for refugees entering Brazil.
    - Letter from Razovsky to Louisa Lorch, São Paulo, Brazil., July 1 and 22, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Razovsky has received the copy of the letter Rosenheim sent to Lorch (See Item #21). Mr. Borchardt, recently returned from Brazil, is not hopeful regarding Brazil accepting refugee children.
    - Executive Office Memo #65, William Haber., July 26, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Effective August 1, 1940, Razovsky will be promoted from Director of Migration Department to Assistant to the Executive Director. Augusta Mayerson will be the acting Director for the Migration Department.
    - Original German and English translation of letter from Luiza Lorch, São Paulo, Brazil to Razovsky., July 30, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Lorch encloses a copy of a letter she wrote to Mrs. Feigenblatt (See Item #16). Attached are the original German letter and the English translation from Lorch to Mrs. Louis Feigenblatt, San Jose, Costa Rica. Lorch describes the women's organization in São Paulo and the children's home.
    - Memo from Frederick W. Borchardt to Razovsky., July 31, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      The Klabin family is trying to get the Brazilian government to bring 300 refugee children into Brazil. He has written to Louisa Lorch for a recent update. Attached is the original German letter from Kaete Rosenheim to Razovsky, July 4, 1940 (See Item #21) and an English translation of Rosenheim's letter dated July 11, 1940 (See Item #22).
    - English letter from Kaete Rosenheim to Razovsky., August 13, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Rosenheim thanks Razovsky for her letter dated July 22nd, she asks if Razovsky would again write to Brazil.
    - Letter from Robert Pilpel, American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, to Razovsky., September 4, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Pilpel encloses a translated letter from the Joint in La Pax, Bolivia, August 23, 1940. This letter, addressed to Frederick W. Borchardt, NRS, discusses "the cold shoulder," the U.S. Consul in Bolivia occasionally shows to refugees.
    - German letter and English translation from Luiza Lorch to Razovsky., August 23, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Lorch needs to wait until next week to reply to the Reichsvereinigung and will keep Razovsky informed. She asks after Dr. Davidson.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Herbert S. Frieder, Jewish Refugee Committee, Manila, Philippines., September 10, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Razovsky asks Frieder of the possibility of getting refugee children to the Philippines.
    - Memo enclosing the Meeting minutes for the New York section of NCJW, August 28, 1940., September 10, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Meeting discusses individual cases.
    - Report by Razovsky regarding S.S. Quanza., September 16, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to American Consul, Moscow, U.S.S.R., December 6, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      She encloses affidavits for visa applications for Dr. Davidson's two sisters, Leah Litivicaite Margulienes and Dvoira Bernstein.
    - Memo from B.J. Klein, Relief and Service, NRS to Razovsky and other staff., December 16 and 19, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Regarding illegal cases. Attached is a report "Recapitulation of Illegals."
  - Relief Work, undated, 1940-1945 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Report by unknown, suggesting amendments to the immigration and naturalization laws., December 1940 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Confidential report by Overseas News Agency. "A Report on Brazil.", January 1, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of letter and memo signed by William Rosenwald to U.S. President., March 6, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Rosenwald has prepared the memo with Joseph P. Chamberlain from NRS and others to amend the existing naturalization laws. Cover letter from Rosenwald to Edwin M. Watson, Secretary to President, asks Watson to forward the enclosed letter and memo to the President.
    - Letter from A.M. Warren, Chief Visa Division to Razovsky., March 24, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      He has received her letter of March 18, 1941 concerning the immigration cases of her brother-in-law Joseph Bernstein, his wife Deborah, and their daughter Anna.
    - Copy of memo to Razovsky., April 21, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Enclosing a report regarding Walter Furnberg and Father Odo, refugees who are in the United States assisting others to obtain visas.
    - Telegram from Razovsky to American Consul Vienna., May 13, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Razovsky inquires after Hermine Krueger, who headed a former trade school for girls in Vienna. Includes affidavit signed by Razovsky.
    - Letter from Albert Abrahamson to Razovsky., July 8, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Abrahamson defines Razovsky's duties at Assistant to the Executive Director.
    - Letter from Alan Cranston, Common Council for American Unity to Razovsky., September 17, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Cranston writes generalities.
    - Letter from Donald Perry, Chief Alien Registration Division to Razovsky., September 19, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Perry verifies the date she and Chamberlain will meet with him.
    - Letter from R. Keith Kane, Assistant Chief Special Defense Unit to Razovsky., September 20, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Regards meeting mentioned in Item #9.
    - Copy of letter from Julius Huttner in Sweden to Razovsky., November 9, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Regards individual case.
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky., December 2, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Requests a list of persons on temporary status unable to obtain own affidavits.
    - Report by Razovsky, concerning hearings on visa rejections., January 21, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Attached is a memo from Dorothy C. Kahn to Family Service Department, regarding appeals on visa applications.
    - Copy of letter from E.E. Salisbury, Immigration and Naturalization Service., February 4, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Letter responds to a client of International Migration Service, who had difficulties attempting to enter Canada following preexamination at Ellis Island.
    - Copy of report from Augusta Mayerson, Director of NRS Migration Department. "Statement for Sub-Committee to Consider Problems Arising from Proposed Curtailment of Change of Status for Aliens on Temporary Visas in the United States.", February 11, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Report from Razovsky. "Procedure Regarding Review of Applications for Immigration Visas by Interdepartmental Review Committee, State Department.", February 18, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Report from Razovsky. "Procedure Regarding Review of Applications for Immigration Visas by Interdepartmental Review Committee, State Department.", April 20, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letter from Augusta Mayerson, Director Migration Department NRS to Charles H. Jordan, Director Joint Relief Committee, Havana, Cuba., June 12, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Concerning individual case.
    - Letter from Charles A. Riegelman to Razovsky., September 1, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Riegelman requests an introduction to Mr. Harrison, Commissioner of Immigration, concerning "internment of alien enemies."
    - Memo from Earl G. Harrison, Commissioner of Immigration to Social, Civic and Welfare Agencies., November 5, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Outlines the methods the Immigration and Naturalization Service processes "aliens of enemy nationalities."
    - Letter from Alwin G. Stieglitz, Chairman, Westchester County Coordinating Committee for Emigres (White Plains, N.Y.) to "Friend," November 27, 1942., October 1, 1941-October 1, 1942, November 27, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      No annual meeting will be held. Attached is an analysis of the committee's case load from October 1, 1941 - October 1, 1942.
    - Letter from Joseph Savoretti, Acting Commissioner, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Philadelphia, to Razovsky., December 18, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Summarizes new procedure for extending temporary stays.
    - Letter from Razovsky to William Rosenwald, President NRS., December 28, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      She does not object to a cut in salary, or her new title Consultant on Migration, and she asks for another meeting before she makes her final decision. Attached is a letter, same date. She asks for clarification of her proposed new position responsibilities.
    - Letter from Albert Abrahamson, Executive Director NRS to Razovsky., January 8, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Details her new status.
    - Memo from Albert Abrahamson to Razovsky., January 8, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Asks for her decision by signing the enclosed letter. Letter concerns the new preexamination procedure. Copy of letter from Earl G. Harrison to Read Lewis, Executive Director Common Council for American Unity. Harrison's letter specifies the changes that would simplify the process.
    - Copy of memo from Albert Abrahamson., January 12, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Abrahamson clarifies Razovsky's responsibilities.
    - Copy of tables. "Immigrants Admitted and Aliens Deported, Total and Hebrews, Fiscal Years 1921 to 1942.", January 13, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Also includes Fiscal Years 1931 to 1942.
    - Memo from Abrahamson to Razovsky., March 2, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Memo relates to illegal immigrants who have resided in the U.S. for over seven years and cannot change their status due to petty crime or "moral turpitude."
    - Letter from A.M. Warren, Dominican Republic to Razovsky., March 18, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      He received her request late. Does she still need him to write a recommendation letter?
    - Copy of report by Razovsky. "Deportation - United States Style.", May 17, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of memo by unknown. "Memorandum Regarding Desirability of Change of Status for Temporary Residents in the USA.", March 23, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of letter from A.M. Warren, Dominican Republic to Francis Sayre, Special Assistant to Secretary of State., April 2, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Recommends Razovsky as a candidate for Governor Lehman's organization as an Immigration Specialist.
    - Memo from Marchel Kovarsky, NRS to staff., April 7, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      An emergency fund has been made available for refugee educators, artists, and researchers to use in fellowships.
    - Copy of memo from Augusta Mayerson, NRS to staff., April 13, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Two law firms are working on obtaining refunds for 1938 and 1939 unused steamship tickets held by German refugees.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Albert Abrahamson., April 15, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Razovsky's resignation letter, effective April 15, 1943.
    - Letter from Razovsky to Joseph E. Beck., April 15, 1943 and May 3, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Razovsky wished to leave her position at once, but is willing to wait until June 1st.
    - Memo from Joseph E. Beck to Razovsky., April 15, 1943 and May 4, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      "... As I understood it, your decision was based on the fact that you are not able to accept the arrangements which had been finally approved by the Executive Committee." He requested that she stay until June 15th.
    - Letter from Charles A. Riegelman, NRS Vice-President and Chairman of the Executive Committee to Razovsky., May 4, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      The January agreement cannot be modified except in terms of her title.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Charles A. Riegelman., May 12, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Her letter of resignation still stands, and her last day will be June 15th.
    - Letter from Dr. Richard Gruenberg to Razovsky., June 15, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      He encloses a copy of a letter sent to him by Edward J. Ennis, Alien Enemy Control Unit. "... You may imagine the delight and satisfaction which this letter aroused; and I suppose, you also will feel a certain satisfaction to see your painstaking work bearing gradually fruits..." Dr. Gruenberg has been permitted to continue his medical profession in the U.S.
    - Copy of letter from Julius Ehrlich to Razovsky., January 24, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      The Erhlich's recently became American citizens, and send Razovsky their greatest thanks.
    - Letter from Hertha Kraus, UNRRA Training Center faculty to Razovsky, Common Council for American Unity., July 7, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Kraus requests Razovsky to teach two sessions at the UNRRA Training Center.
    - Copy of letter from Mary C. Bromage, Administrative Assistant and Registrar, UNRRA Training Center, to Razovsky., July 14, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Bromage confirms Razovsky's acceptance of the teaching proposal.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mary C. Bromage., July 18, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Razovsky makes arrangements for her teaching sessions.
    - Report from Jewish Central Information Office in London. "The Position of Jewish Refugees in England.", January 1945 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of report unknown author. "Cases Illustrating Desirability of Change of Status for Temporary Visa Residents in U.S.A.", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of report, unknown author. "Cases Illustrating the Effects of Change of Status.", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of report, unknown author. "Contacts with Nazi Poland, Soviet Poland and Central Government of Poland.", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Details mailing service; location of relatives; money, food, and clothing transmissions.
    - Copy of report, "from a 20 year old girl.", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Author's personal experience in Yugoslavia after Nazi Germany took over. Author was a student at the state's teachers training college.
    - Copy of memo, unknown author. "Memorandum Regarding Functions of Lehman Commission.", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      The Lehman Commission is conceived as providing overseas relief in terms of medical staff and medicine, food and clothing, immigration, and family reunification.)
    - Handwritten letter from Read Lewis to Razovsky., undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Lewis requests Razovsky to set up a meeting concerning "enemy aliens." (See Item #9 and Item #10.)
  - Treatment of Enemy Aliens in wartime, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript, "Treatment of Enemy Aliens in Wartime," unsigned author., undated; 8 pages. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Report, "Alien Enemy Control in War Time," unsigned author., undated; 5 pages. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series V: American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee/United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency, undated, 1946-1950; Box 6, Folders 1-6.
  Folders are arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by subject.
  This series documents Razovsky's work held in various capacities with the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (AJDC) and the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency (UNRRA) from 1944-1946 and 1948. Material includes correspondence, a dramatic sketch, flyers, memorandum, a news clipping, pamphlets, personnel forms, press releases, program invitations, receipts, reports, a speech, telegrams, travel authorizations, and a V-mail.
  Box 6, Folder 1 contains material from Razovsky's positions as a Displaced Personals Specialist for the European Missions Reserve for UNRRA, which she held from October 1944-October 1945; and as a consultant for UNRRA Office of Public Information, which she held from October 1945-February 1946. UNRRA loaned Razovsky in February 1945 to the AJDC, Paris, France to organize the AJDC's Personal Service Division, a division that focused on the problems of newly released refugees from concentration camps. Box 6, Folder 1 includes travel authorizations, personnel action notices, and salary and expenses reports concerning Razovsky's transfer to AJDC. Razovsky's work is summarized in a biographical sketch (see October 1944 ) and a work progress report (see February 23, 1945 ).
  Box 6, Folder 1 also documents the experiences of displaced persons as reported by Razovsky, witnesses, and the survivors themselves. A letter written and signed by 115 Jewish refugees from Concentration Camp Natzweiler-Vailhingen/Enz appeals to the French Government to put them in contact with AJDC, Paris (see letters in English and French dated April 14, 1945 and April 20, 1945 ). Letters written to US military Chaplain Judah Nadich (see letters dated April 22, 1945, May 1, 1945 and May 21, 1945 ) and a letter and report written by Joseph Eaton (see report dated April 21, 1945 and letter dated May 13, 1945 ) describe survivors from concentration camps and the inadequate state of relief given to displaced persons. Razovsky's report dated May 25, 1945 recounts interviews she had with refugees at a local relief office. In a June 8, 1945 letter, AJDC Assistant Secretary, Louis H. Sobel describes the negotiations, transport, and care, of which Razovsky took part, of 535 children from Camp Buchenwald to Palestine and 350 children to Switzerland. A letter from "Sylia," American Red Cross, to "Alice," Hadassah dated June 9, 1945 narrates her experiences of anti-Semitism in the U.S. Army, and portrays Razovsky as "a frustrated, disorganized woman" and points to AJDC's "ineffectiveness." Razovsky reports on June 26, 1945 on a trip to Thionville where she accompanies a group of children from Buchenwald to a displaced persons camp in Metz. A refugee named Maas bemoans the lack of food given to refugees in France. She writes in a letter dated July 6, 1945, "We are wondering if our allies want us deliberately to die and do their utmost to hasten our death..." A memorandum draft from Fred K. Hoehler, Director Division on Displaced Persons, UNRRA to Governor Lehman on September 19, 1945 recommends counteractions to the harsh treatment of anti-Nazis and Jews still left in Germany.